[Music]
so in the series so far
we have discussed a number of aspects of
why the information ecology's broken
why it is so hard to make sense of
what's really going on in the world why
people are coming to such kind of
radically polarized positions on almost
everything
and a little bit of why that's really
consequential for our ability to make
good choices or do anything if we have a
hard time coming to even
a base shared understanding of what is
uh in this one near the end we're going
to get into a project we're working on
that has been a pretty central focus for
how to start to repair the information
ecology
that we are hopeful about excited about
and want to invite people to
participate in but we want to start by
spending the first chunk kind of
recapping
the problem space hopefully making it
more succinct clear
and maybe addressing a few parts that we
haven't so far
[Music]
when kovid came a lot of people were
hoping that that could be a shared enemy
for the whole world it could unite the
world a virus is almost like an alien
invader right that
isn't it isn't human it isn't even like
us
we're all threatened by it can we all
unite together to share scientific info
and production of uh
[Music]
medical supplies and those types of
things i remember that that was like a
very naive hope that a number of people
were suggesting at the very beginning of
covid that might come from this and i
think we've seen
almost as far from that as we can see
we've seen
polarization on how to handle it in
almost every country
and between countries
and on almost every sub-topic whether
it's hydroxychloroquine or
masks or shutdown or vaccines
there's kind of polarization across the
whole space we've seen the entire global
order has already shifted
right u.s china relations were already
tense but they got very magnified in
this situation
the tensions in the eu got very
magnified the relationships between the
eu and eastern europe
those tensions got magnified so
um i think covid was just a big enough
issue
to start to set off the systemic
fragilities that were already in
place
[Music]
so yeah i think we were sitting right
here having this conversation
i don't know a year ago or something uh
before covid and we were talking about
the breakdown incense making that was
already occurring
making it uh
increasing the speed at which systemic
fragility
was being actuated and at which
catastrophic risk was impending but then
since covid
and then since the riots and the fires
and the
so many types of dynamics increase
militarized tension in various parts of
the world
i think everyone feels quite differently
about it they have a
sense of not just that some people are
saying there might be impending
catastrophe but that we're in the
process of that and that it's not just
within one air it's cascading
and so what i want to talk about here
today is not just okay there's all these
problems
but why is our assessment of the
one of the main causes of the problems
themselves and the worsening of the
problems and
what would it take for us to have a kind
of shared assessment that makes
solutions possible at all
if we take almost any issue and say what
are the most consequential issues facing
the world today what are the things that
are both hottest in the news cycle and
possibly most consequential
and we start to list them and we say
which of those is there fairly good
consensus
across the space of citizens on it's
like almost nothing
right and not only is there not
consensus but there is nearly maximum
polarization
that is felt to be nearly maximally
consequential which is a basis for
not just social tension but a movement
towards warfare
if you think about the upcoming u.s
elections right now i would say that
we're in a situation that is
unprecedented in
the history of all of our lifetimes and
pretty much unprecedented in the history
of the nation
is everyone has always felt that
presidential elections are consequential
maybe they've even felt that they're
more consequential than they really are
and they get passionate about it but
right now
the percentage of the population that
thinks that it's not just consequential
this election but is existential to the
republic itself
is very high like it's a very high
percentage of the population that think
the
way this election goes will be either
the end of the nation or the possibility
of it to continue on both sides
right so like to really get a sense the
trump supporters feel that trump is the
only thing standing between
the republic being protected and the
people being protected at all and a kind
of globalist deep state cabal taking
everything over in a finalizing way and
running the benign china hypothesis like
they did in dc since the 70s and
basically ceding control of the world to
china
that kind of thing the the never
trumpers think that if trump gets in
he will eviscerate the last elements of
a republican created a dynasty
kind of for his family and chosen people
to run it like they both think that it's
the end of the republic if the other guy
gets in
and they both think the other side is
going to steal it they're set up
to actually think that there isn't
election security it's going to be
stolen so what happens when the election
comes
and it's not held as valid and it's held
as existential and we have these
mounting tensions
already that were there with kovid
because of lockdown lockdown means more
news cycle to take all the stuff in
right and
then also it means radically increasing
unemployment
and we so when we saw the violence start
with george floyd
violence was actually bound to start
from some trigger
when you study kind of the societal
chaos indices the things that would
create a basis for societal chaos
the more people whose fundamental needs
aren't met by a system they become more
desperately willing to act against the
system
and so when you start having massive
unemployment that's a very unstable
situation for the overall system and
it's going to express itself somehow
and no one really has the ability to
process any of this
well nor are the nor is the reporting
oriented to try to process it in an
adequate way which is actually a really
hard thing to do
there's much higher incentive to control
a narrative for particular purposes
and so for the most part people have
kind of traded epistemology for
tribalism
meaning given up on trying to do a
rigorous job of making sense of things
themselves like take a narrative take a
q anon narrative
take a antifa narrative break it into
individual propositions
and then look at each of those
propositions what evidence do i have to
verify it or falsify it
maybe neither do i have any evidence
that would at least support or refute it
do other people interpret that evidence
differently go across the whole thing
then look at
alternate hypotheses nobody does that
right like very very few people
use formal epistemic process so what
they're really doing
is paying attention to what feels true
which largely has to do with what people
like
me kind of seem to think and which team
i kind of want to be on
and what i'm getting exposed to the most
[Music]
let's just take a historical perspective
for a minute
humans have been here for a long time
but the thing that we call civilization
which was much larger than tribal
scale starting to organize early egypt
or sumeria or whatever
since the beginning of that larger scale
coordination
a tiny percentage of the people that
ever lived lived in something like a
republic or democracy
they almost all lived in a feudalism or
monarchy or some kind
of much more top-down autocratic system
which is actually quite easy to
understand because the proposition of a
republic or democracy a participatory
governance is actually a wild
proposition
which is that a huge number of people
who don't know each other who want
different things can sublimate their
desire and difference
to coordinate with each other it's like
that's actually kind of oh
it's understandable that's a hard thing
right this is why corporations aren't
run that way corporations are
autocracies
and so the few times throughout history
that a republic or a democracy emerged
they're actually really kind of worth
studying and i'm going to simplify here
but
it's a fair simplification they emerged
following a period of a cultural
enlightenment for that culture
and the cultural enlightenments always
had at least a couple things in common
so if we look at the
kind of early greek democracies the
athenian democracy of course we can
criticize that there's a lot that wasn't
perfect about it but it was a movement
in the direction of
more participatory governance it was
following
the kind of greek enlightenment that
both had a very high value on classical
education for everyone let's have
everybody learn history let's have them
all learn philosophy let's have them all
learn
formal logic and rhetoric and the arts
and these types of things
so that everyone can have a sense of how
to know the true
plus the good and the beautiful right
like all of in integrated sense of those
understand what types of systems worked
and didn't work in the past because of
more kind of knowledge of history
so if everyone can basically sense base
reality
on their own well which has to be
trained right like
there's actually training involved in
that and then there was also the value
of the socratic dialogue
and in the socratic dialogue everybody
is being trained to be able to take
every perspective i can argue this side
then i can move around and argue this
side
if people are being trained in that kind
of
dialectical process that means i'm being
trained in seeking to understand the
perspective of others
and actually be able to argue them even
better which is steel manning
right well if you have a bunch of people
who can all understand reality on their
own well
and they can have high quality
conversations and take each other's
perspective not just
go into tribalism and otherness and make
a
villain or a straw man of the other
those people can start to have the kinds
of conversations to share sense making
that leads to being able to make
collective choices and then they don't
need rulers and they can say like we can
throw the rulers off
and do a participatory governance system
the european enlightenment which led
to the foundation of the u.s and a
reformation of a lot of kind of european
and other global
governance the kind of modern era
similarly was
the renaissance right the idea that
people would be renaissance men or
renaissance people who
actually train in lots of disciplines
not just be
specialists because it's very hard if
someone's just a specialist to make
sense of the world
right and or for them to talk to each
other across those
specialist languages so the idea of
renaissance person
and then of natural philosophy and
science that we can actually empirically
tell what's going on and have the same
conversation
based on that plus kind of the hegelian
dialectic
we can seek a thesis and then seek an
antithesis and then see is there
a higher order synthesis if people can
do that well
a town hall is a possible thing in a
republic or a democracy or participatory
government
governance is a possible thing if that
starts to break down
where people can't actually make sense
of reality on their own well so they're
taking the view of authorities who can
then be captured because of the power of
that and used for power purposes
and they can't take the view of other
people well they can only basically make
strawmen and fight against them
there is no possibility for collective
choice making which is what a democracy
republic's about collective choice
making
if there's no capacity for collective
right the antecedents of
choice making is collective sense making
collective meaning making and collective
conversation
collective sense making of what's
actually going on
and what do we anticipate the effects of
a particular action to be
collective meaning making of what's
important well we're focused on
different things that are important can
we factor all of them and try to come up
with a design solution
that is good for all of them right now
we don't even have a process in
democracy for that we have
somebody's focused on something they
come up with a proposition to benefit
that they don't even think about the
fact that that proposition harms other
things because they're focused on the
subset of values they're focused on
which is why almost no proposition gets
a hundred percent or zero percent of the
vote it's like fifty percent because
the people who are focused on what it
benefits really want it and the people
who are focused on what at harm's really
don't want it
that inherently and unavoidably
polarizes the population against each
other
because i see the thing that you are
desperately trying to make happen
is actively harming the thing that i
hold as sacred worth fighting for
so i have to hold you as an enemy right
but it was because of a dumb proposition
it was because of a proposition that
didn't even try to get hey
you don't necessarily need that economic
thing to go through or that tax policy
or that oil policy you need your kids to
be able to have an opportunity for a
real job and to be able to own a house
someday like
not be in in economic servitude forever
well if i hold just what is the value
without the strategy that's attached to
it that contextualizes it having it
happen that way i'm like
that's fair i economic servitude's a
problem and
i don't hold that that thing can't go
through i hold that we don't want an
extinct species
in this area you're like i actually like
forests
not extincting species would be cool i
just i'm willing to do it if that's the
only way my kids aren't in servitude
forever
if we start by taking the what are the
values that everyone holds and say
is there a proposition that does a
better job of meeting these and can we
use some collective sense making
for collective design well it's like
that's so obvious once you say it and
that's not in our democratic process at
all
but it also requires people that can
have a good quality conversation and
seek to hear what other people's values
are
and would want to seek not just the
immediacy of war which then of course
you never just win forever right you win
and the thing that won the other side
reverse engineers makes better and comes
back
and so then you just get an arms race
and an escalation of narrative warfare
info warfare memetic warfare tribalism
physical kinetic warfare all of those
types of things
you know when we say that most people
throughout the history of civilization
haven't lived in democracies and that or
republics and that when those have
occurred they've occurred following
periods of cultural enlightenment
they also then haven't lasted very long
right historically
they've lasted 300 years at most most of
the time
and of course every empire breaks down
no empire lasts forever which is one of
the kind of key insights is that right
now we have a fully globalized system
and it's in the process of breakdown
where all of the previous
systems did break down but they were
localized and so the
the consequence of this is different in
kind
but the democracies break down much
faster than
many of the dynasties and other types of
top-down systems because it's just
easier for a small number of people to
coordinate with each other than a large
number of people
right you think about it it's kind of
like if somebody is a bodybuilder it
takes a lot of work to keep that much
muscle on
right they have to be working out and
eating all the time the moment they stop
it starts breaking down because it's
it's actually very expensive well it's
actually very expensive to keep a whole
population
highly educated and highly engaged not
just kind of in their own life
but really paying attention like most
people don't want to go to jury duty
they don't go to town halls they don't
really want to pay attention to the
issues well
and this is part of why the breakdown
occurs is
if somebody works very hard to fight a
revolutionary war against a tyrant or to
try and overthrow a tyrannical system of
governance or whatever
they have an embodied knowledge of what
the bad alternative is
and they work very hard to make sure
their kids have that so that's why
a washington or franklin would say those
types of things right like
that it's utterly necessary for everyone
to have this kind of comprehensive
education because they know what the
alternative
is but as time goes on and three
generations pass and four do
the idea of a monarchy or of a
totalitarian system or whatever it's
just not even a thing we don't have any
embodied relationship to it we aren't
scared of it
it doesn't motivate us to do the very
hard work to understand how to be
actively engaged citizens
and there's stuff on tv right and
there's like stuff to do and there's
social interests and there's whatever
else and
so there is a lack of generational
knowledge transfer of the real critical
issue
that someone fought hard to form a new
system so the basis of what it takes to
make that system ends up breaking down
and we can see we are at a place where
this this is not a system of foreign by
the people the people
at best every four years get riled up
over a person that they
didn't really have much to say in which
people were even there or what they do
propositionally or anything else
and so what i would say is you know the
u.s is at about 250 years
since it was founded they don't make it
past 300 years this one has had
more pressure to break down on it
because since world war
ii in the bretton woods world it's been
the center of a global order so everyone
who's wanted to change the global order
has had a maximum incentive
to try to influence dc in various
directions and it's not that hard
to flow money into the dc structure
internationally
towards whatever your personal interests
are it's not that hard for a foreign
actor a state actor or non-state actor
to be able it's so it's not just
economic capture within the country it's
also international this is not just for
the u.s this is everywhere the u.s
just happens to be a kind of central
example right now but it's not that hard
to
have money go from a sovereign wealth
fund or something like that into an
international igo or ngo
into a corporation in the u.s that uh
has certain kinds of veils and
protections or a non-profit into
the washington dc think tank non-profit
political action campaign complex and
start to
purchase legislators and get senators
invested in doing the bidding of
particular things and whatever else
and so when both the left and right
feel like the nation is on the brink of
existential collapse they're right
the integrity of the thing actually is
their answer as to what the solution is
isn't right
so this this one will not continue
to have the to actually be a republic
and be able to help influence the rest
of the world in a positive direction it
just won't it is
in kind of a decay process the question
is whether it decays into
uh just less and less function and
irrelevance or whether it decays and
reboots
and if we reboot an actual kind of
meaningful
participatory governance and
obviously that's a u.s question but it's
a global question
and in order to do that a cultural
enlightenment as a prerequisite
is necessary right the cultural
enlightenment of
is everyone recognizing that collective
choice making
has to be based on collective sense
making collective meaning making
collective conversation and are we
starting to really invest
not in doubling down on our own bias but
in the capacity to make sense of things
well
the capacity to understand why other
people are thinking the things that they
do
and what signal is in there and what
noise is in there
and the capacity to communicate well so
we can coordinate
either that becomes a widespread value
that we start investing in
and training in or it will devolve into
autocracy and we should actually put
attention on
trying to pick how to make it a better
monarchy than a worse one
benjamin franklin i believe said
something to the effect of
if i could have a government without a
newspaper a newspaper without a
government
i would pick the newspaper and the
reason is and of course he was talking
about an independent high quality fourth
estate that creates an information
commons
information commons or epistemic commons
is an important concept that i think
everybody needs to have
which is when we think of the commons we
think about some shared
aspect of the world that is both a
resource that we have shared access to
but also some shared stewardship of
we don't have very good commons
management today in lots of ways and we
can see tragedy of the commons type
dynamics because of that but we think of
the air as an example of a commons or
the ocean or whatever
well the information commons is what is
the what is the space of information out
there
about what is true that informs our
capacity to
make choices and we can see that just
like
a smokestack billowing pollution into
the air
most of what is being put into the
information commons is pollution right
it's a lot of noise and not true stuff
or stuff that is
partially true with spin to advance some
agentic interests
because most interests when they're
communicating are communicating to get
people to believe something that is
useful for them
and particularly the more powerful they
are they use that asymmetric power
to both maintain and increase their
asymmetric
power we can see that since covid like
the market's crashed and then they've
bounced back up but employment hasn't
correspondingly gone bad a cup real
production in the underlying market and
real wealth of the people relative to
their purchasing power hasn't gone up
a few billionaires wealth has you know
radically gone up so we see the
both radical power asymmetry represented
in finance
um and the decoupling of the actual
you know economy in the market
so the information commons is the thing
we're talking about here and in some
ways i would say the information commons
is
more important than the other ones to
pay attention to because it's the basis
of why
any of us would make the choices we
would that would determine how we affect
the air or the ocean
or war or anything else and
so i would say the quality of the
information commons is
requisite and that is both like the
quality of public education
and the quality of media news
and you can see in all the kind of
founding documents for this country
those were both considered prerequisites
for the ongoing protection of the
republic
that there would be very high quality
public education where everyone learned
the civics necessary to really
participate
and a independent high quality fourth
estate so people could know what was
going on currently so they could
participate
meaningfully and effectively and we know
that
institutions decay for a number of
reasons and we've seen radical decay in
the fourth estate and in
public education and in kind of
government writ large as a result
it's also important to understand that
it's not just that
democracies and republics require high
quality information even markets do
if you read ann rand
and other kind of laissez-faire market
ideology it talks about the need for
accurate and symmetrical information for
the rational actors to be able to make
good choices in the market right
the idea that a rational actor can see
all of the information and make a good
choice and as a result the best products
and services at the best price
are what get up regulated well if i'm
not
if i can't see all the things because
there's way too many of them
and so then the algorithms that
determine what i see end up
affecting my choice and if i'm not
actually a rational actor doing really
good sense making
that has the info to compare what a
better product or service is
whoever does better marketing that
emotionally compels me ends up winning
rather than better product and service
so the system starts to incent
extraction
over real production value so all of our
large systems of coordination whether
they're more state-like systems or
market-like systems require accurate and
symmetrical information for people to
make good choices
so if we if we think about how have
humans ever thought about coordinating
at scale
there's a bunch of models that different
social scientists have put together i'll
share
one there but there's different ways of
thinking about so we don't need to
attach too hard but you'll kind of get
the gist
there are market type mechanisms for
large-scale coordination
there are government or state-like
mechanisms and there are culture-like
mechanisms and we can kind of define all
those differently but market type
mechanisms mean
um some kind of distributed bottom-up
type system where the
agreement happens point-to-point not as
a systemic agreement across the whole
space and the topology is emergent
and whether it is a formal religious
organization or a state or some kind of
commons agreement
then you have the government type
mechanisms that have some top-down
collective agreement type structure
those are kind of different
architectures
but then you have like culture and by
culture here because that word means
different things in different places i
mean what are the
collective values that people hold
and the collective worldview and ways of
making sense
that would determine say in a government
what laws should be made right because
law is really a codification of an
ethical system
ethics is then not part of the market or
part of the state formally but
is supposed to be guiding and binding
them and so
we can think of that as kind of like a
culture and so if you think about those
three and how they're supposed to
interact
in the idea of like our current system a
liberal democracy of some sort
roughly is that most of the innovation
will happen and most of the exchange of
goods and
services and the kind of flow of
resource and resource allocation
will happen in the market
but the reason that we have a liberal
democracy that has a state
as opposed to just a pure market and
many people will talk about this reason
differently but like
the kind of foundational reason that is
argued for
is that markets will have a market for
human trafficking
or for organ harvesting or for organized
crime or
maybe to cut all the wood in an area
down and there's no state park left or
whatever it is so
there can be perverse incentives in
markets that are
good in the short term but really bad in
the long term or good for some people
bad for others and so we say okay
there are some things market does
innovation and production well but it
also does
extraction and kind of pathological
stuff so we want to bind
the predatory aspects of market well how
do we do that well we'll make a state
and we'll give it this thing called rule
of law and then we'll give it this thing
called monopoly of violence which is the
police force internally
that can so we make a national
forest right so we're not going to cut
down the trees here we can cut down the
trees here but not here
and then if someone goes and is cutting
the trees down there the cops are going
to show up and if those guys have guns
the cops have bigger guns a monopoly of
violence because without enforcement
law doesn't really mean anything right
it's just kind of a suggestion
and then incentive is still going to be
the thing that runs it so this is a
system that
supposedly rather than based on
incentive can bind predatory incentive
so the purpose of the state primarily is
to check the predatory aspects of market
where people would have an incentive
to do something that we kind of
collectively want to agree is not a
thing to do
but then the people are supposed to bind
and check the state
that's the idea of governance up for and
by the people is
how do we ensure that the people that
the market interests where the money and
the power is
don't just uh capture
the regulatory interests and say hey
change this thing in my benefit
and your swiss bank account will get
filled up and you'll have a house to use
in the hamptons and whatever else
well the only way to ensure that you
don't get regulatory capture is if
there's
enough transparency in government and
the people are educated enough and
actively involved that they get to see
that the government is actually doing
rule of law rather than other things
think about how far the citizens here or
pretty much anywhere
are from being able to understand the
issues that are happening at the level
of
federal government and actually have
transparent insight and are actively
involved in a way that would kind of
police the thing
so of course then what happens is you do
get regulatory capture
because as the people aren't checking
the state the state stops checking the
market the predatory aspects of the
market the market starts to follow a
power law distribution
and those who have the most resources
who have asymmetric power have both the
capacity and the incentive
to increase their asymmetric power and
that's through a bunch of things it's
through marketing and affecting the
mindsets of the people it's through
affecting news and media it's through
the capture of regulatory systems
all of those different types of dynamics
and the last part of this system so
the state checks the market the people
check the state
then the market or the underlying
economy itself
checks the people which means that the
thing that the people want the
accounting actually has to work they
can't all want to extract more from the
system than anyone is putting in
if you really think about that there's
actually a beautiful and kind of
stabilizing
complex geometry to it but at the base
of it
is the capacity of the people as a whole
to make good choices and whether it's
how they're acting in the market how
they're acting in the state
checking it if people can't make sense
of the types of issues
the world is facing and that the states
will be making choices on and that the
markets are affecting
if they can't make sense of that well
and they can't communicate about it well
all of those systems start to be
captured
[Music]
lying is not a new thing right putting
spin on information isn't a new thing
being wrong about stuff isn't a new
thing uh
and intentionally being able to try to
control the narrative for purposes
narrative warfare and information
warfare aren't new things you can read
about them in sun tzu and other
you know thousands of year-old military
doctrine texts of
how to control the population through
making false enemies and through
deception and whatever
so this always been a thing and like
very active disinformation how do you
have some of your
messengers have a message about what the
attack plan is that you know they'll get
captured so that the other side gets
what the secret intel is and the whole
thing was a farce to get them to make
the wrong choice like
thousands of years old craftiness around
the stuff
but we've also then worked on counter
strategies how do we come divergent
and as vehement and so it has been
degrading
there's a bunch of reasons i won't cover
all of them but i will address a couple
of the main ones so people understand it
because the solution space requires
understanding the problem space
that's actually a general kind of
principle of sense making is
uh the saying by charles kettering if
you
a problem fully understood is half
solved
but that also means a problem not fully
understood is pretty much unsolvable
and so we typically have very
superficial understandings of problems
don't understand the
the generator and the etiology of them
well enough and what they're connected
to and we try to jump straight to
solutions and so the solutions are
either
gibberish or actually bad um and then in
gender counter responses for
understandable reasons
so um to try to understand the problem
of the breakdown and sense making a
little more so we can think about
adequate solutions
one of the biggest things and this has
been talked about on rebel wisdom before
i believe you've had tristan harris on
who talked about this very centrally is
the movement from
news being largely broadcast media
uh mediated to decentralized media
mediated which was the internet and then
not just the internet but
um the large internet information
curation platforms
facebook in particular but also youtube
and various other ones
it's important to understand why this is
such a big deal
is all of our global institutions
evolved in the context of broadcast
media right from the printing press
through the telegram to the radio to the
tv it was still
a small number of groups being able to
have
some narrative on what's true and be
able to broadcast it and everybody get
that now of course that means it was
susceptible to very centralized control
and capture
but at least when everybody was watching
cnn they at least all
saw the same base reality they could
agree or disagree maybe they were
informed or misinformed but there was at
least some basis of
what they're being exposed to because
right now people are really
riled up over issues that they have no
on the ground knowledge of
right like they they weren't on the
ground where the shooting was they
weren't in beirut they aren't in north
korea they
so their sense of what's going on
is mediated through the media right
through what's coming through this kind
of 2d
screen and so there was in broadcast at
least a sense of
shared base information about the world
beyond my own experience my own direct
experience
as soon as we started to get to and you
know the internet there was this very
libertarian beautiful idea
that it would democratize broadcast so
rather than a few billionaires being
able to control broadcast you could go
to youtube and
everybody could broadcast and so it
would democratize the ability to share
information
and then if it was true that we had kind
of a
market of rational actors who would
parse the information and up regulate
the signal of the best stuff wouldn't
that be awesome
of course nearly the exact opposite
thing happened because
so much broadcast gets put up that i
google something and i get a billion
search results for anything
well i can never read through a billion
search results to be a rational actor
and make sense of
that entire space nor can i do the deep
parsing on any one of those things
so then of the billion search results
which ones do i actually
see that became one of the big problems
was how do we curate the content to show
people the stuff that they
want to see well now that starts to
become a big problem so you get
something like facebook for instance
having a tremendous amount of ability to
harvest very particular information
about me that is unique to me not just
even a demographic
whereas the broadcast news on a tv
didn't have that i could tell if i
turned it on or turned it off and that
was about it but i wasn't interacting
with it in a way that could give me a
tremendous
could give them a tremendous amount of
personalized micro targeting information
but now i'm on facebook and what i like
and what i share and what i comment on
what my mouse hovers over the analytics
of all of that or such
that after i've done about 300 likes
facebook can predict what i will like
better than my spouse
and after i've gone further it actually
has a psychographic profile on me that
is asymmetric to anything that any human
cia agent or whatever could have ever
had previously
and that was co-occurring with i'm
carrying my cell phone around all the
time that is both tracking stuff that
i'm doing and using notifications to
give me a continuous feed so there's a
radical
increase in the amount of input into my
mind space and the amount of data being
harvested about me across platforms
to be able to micro target of those
billion
things which ones i should see now it
happens to be that we think of facebook
or youtube or whatever as a tool
but it is actually a corporate interest
that has agency
that is not just a tool and
so those corporations make money by
selling advertising selling information
and they sell more advertising by
maximizing my engagement
and maximizing my time on site well i
don't want to spend that much time
scrolling facebook because i have
to do so if i stay in my kind of
prefrontal rational cortex
i will check it real quickly and then go
because i have stuff to do
but i'll spend more time if i get
limbicly hijacked if i get into social
fomo of like am i going to miss out on
what's happening or if i get outraged or
scared or whatever it is so
and i'm also not going to spend as much
time on stuff that is totally foreign to
me as stuff that i already know is
important
so what happens is the ai that is paying
attention to what i engage with the most
that is curating all of the information
on facebook or the internet to
me is curating what is stickiest and
what is stickiest is a
very much like foods that are addictive
are usually bad for you salad's not that
addictive french fries are much more
addictive
information that is maximally sticky is
usually actually
because it is appealing to dopaminergic
hijacks
so what it curates for is a combination
of bias
and limbic hijack which is outrage
group identity and certainty and
so now what we have is a situation where
because there's so much stuff
so much total stuff online the curation
platforms
and it's important to understand that
the ais that are doing that
are radically more powerful than the ai
that several years ago beat kasparov at
chess
like a much more powerful game theoretic
ai than that that is controlling
the information feed of what i believe
to try to maximize stickiness and i
don't even realize i'm playing that game
right so this is an asymmetric
information warfare
that is un like the asymmetry that ever
could exist in the past this is so many
orders of magnitude more asymmetric
and so i might have someone
who is in oakland who they look on their
facebook feed and they just see
cops killing black people like their
whole facebook feed is this and people
who
are recognizing and outraged by it and
then kind of what looks like clan and
nazi members and
because that actually maximizes their
time on site and their sharing an
engagement that maximizes other people's
time on site
and i might have somebody in texas trump
supporting and all they see
is people wrongly attacking cops and
black on black violence
and black on white violence and both of
these people are getting vicariously
traumatized
by what they're seeing to the point that
they're having trauma reactions and they
feel like
it's a war zone and they have to pick up
arms and go out into the street
and neither of them are getting
statistical representation of the entire
space right and i can scroll for an hour
and i just keep seeing more of it so it
seems like it's everything but i'm not
even seeing point zero zero one percent
of the total
so everybody's getting increased
certainty outrage trauma
and wider apart from each other right
this is actually really important where
those two people
i might be able to scroll through both
of their news feeds for 10 hours and not
find a single piece of news in common
so the opposite of everybody seeing cnn
now
it seems certain that the all the people
that i know
think like me and all the people that
seem like they're making sense think
like me
and the only version of the other i get
is a pejorative straw man or villainized
version
well of course that tool by itself
will break democracy break republics
break the social fabric of civilization
it is like when we talk about ai risk
we're already dealing with
ai risk that is destroying the fabric of
civilization and driving all these other
issues as second and third order effects
so that's a critical thing to understand
that's not the only thing that is
current but that's both
the emergence of the internet and
everyone being able to broadcast where
there's no quality control in the news
before there could be bad stuff but
there was at least some accountability
of who it was right it was cnn or the
bbc
so if they got something really wrong
there was at least some ftc or whatever
that had quality control now no quality
control
but radical amplification type
possibilities
uh radical information about everyone to
personally micro target them to
to limbicly hijack and
and the cell phone right the continuous
both monitoring and drip
that's the technological landscape
change
simultaneous to that we also see
that because of globalization and the
extent of globalization
the issues that we're facing are more
complex and more abstract than the
issues we evolved to be able to face
so tribes didn't have to think about
climate change and
positive feedback effects on
hydrological cycles in the amazon and
albedo effects or grid stability like
these are
huge and they're they're hyper objects
which means an object i can see with my
senses
a hyper object i can only conceptualize
i can't see
climate change i can see snow melt here
but snow melt here is very different
than the abstract concept of climate
change
and positive albedo effect the same with
like i can see a weapon but i can't
see nuclear risk writ large right
i can't see the information ecology writ
large so i can understand it but we kind
of didn't
evolve to do that well so we have to
train ourselves to do it well or we
we won't so we have a situation where
all the biggest problems are hyper
objects
they're very complex and they're
interconnections of hyperobjects and
we're not trained at all for how to do
that
that's another thing right so the issues
are authentically more complex
the information ecology is oriented to
bias reinforcement limbic hijack bias
reinforcement because i'm more likely to
click on something that sounds important
to me than something that sounds foreign
to me
sounds important means appeals to my
existing understanding and value systems
so that inherently does bias
reinforcement even without the intention
to do so
right and so it's not trying to drive
political polarization it's trying to
drive profit and maximize time on site
and political polarization and
radicalization just happens to be a
second order effect
simultaneous to this is once you already
have a media environment
where people are having much more
radicalized views where it's so complex
they give up on being able to sense make
it themselves so that
everyone kind of becomes an epistemic
nihilist to some degree and
chooses tribalism instead without even
realizing they're doing that
um like what is the group that i want to
be part of that seems more like me what
are the leaders that i
just have a felt sense of trust in more
in that environment it's also way easier
for actors who want to
do narrative warfare to do it
[Music]
let's say that we're talking about any
other state actor
or non-state terrorist actor that wants
to decrease the power of the u.s now we
can also see this is not just happening
to the u.s is happening
the u.s was supporting the protests in
hong kong right like we've done this
throughout the rest of the world
this is the nature of how warfare works
but we'll look at this particular
situation
you don't front on attack the country
with the biggest
military you turn the enemy against
itself
yes and it's not that hard to turn the
enemy against itself when you already
have an environment that is polarizing
and doing that thing all you have to do
is just support the stuff the right
believes
to believe it even more just radicalize
the stuff they already believe and that
the left believes to believe it even
more
so this is where we start to see all
these things about
chinese twitter bots and russian
interference and whatever that
other state actors are actually
affecting the information ecology
to be able to drive radicalization
because that turning the enemy against
itself weakens the entire empire right
now this is happening multi in a
multipolar way across the whole thing so
it's not us versus china
it's radically multi-polar it's
important to understand
the other part here is that even though
none of the superpowers of the world the
major
g8 or g20 whatever nations are in direct
kinetic warfare today
i wouldn't say it's fair to say we're in
peace time either
[Music]
the maybe this is the last piece of
history and then we can kind of move
into the solution space
so throughout the history of the world
the major adjacent empires never had
very long periods of peace like they
war was a part of how they dealt with
conflict right and
at world war ii something changed where
we could never have large-scale war
between the major powers because our
weapons were too big it was too
catastrophic
and so the post-world war ii piece the
bretton woods world
is really unprecedented in the history
of the world because a nuclear bomb is
unprecedented in the history of the
world
until the nuclear bomb we have the
ability to like totally mess
stuff up locally but we didn't have the
ability to kill life on earth right we
didn't have the ability to
induce existential risk so that was the
beginning of it and that was like from
an evolutionary perspective that's like
a second ago
right it's not much time that we got the
bomb
and as a result we said oh we can't
ever have wars again between these major
powers so how do we do that well
it also happens to be that the tech that
gave us the bomb gave us the capacity
for globalization so let's make a
globalization-based world where we're so
economically interdependent
that it's never profitable to go to war
it's more profitable to be in kind of
trade and exchange with each other
well a lot of ways that makes sense
right and we haven't had another
world war since then so it's kind of
made sense but of course what that also
does is it means that you have
a globalized rather than a bunch of
localized systems so
failures anywhere can start cascading to
failures everywhere so the system as a
whole becomes very fragile
it's very interconnected but also very
fragile and we saw this with kovid
a virus in one area could become a virus
everywhere
could become increasing social unrest
everywhere could become breakdowns in
supply chains everywhere
could become decoupling financial
markets and economies everywhere
it's like whoa that's a very
interconnected and fragile world
where failures anywhere can cascade and
there's going to be failures in places
so the cascade potential is just very
high
if you look at the agreements that were
put in place in the bretton woods world
to mediate peace most of them have
broken
right we see the us having pulled out of
nato we see decreased support for the
u.n
we see the having pulled out of the who
and not just during the trump
administration it's been weakening for
some time for
a number of reasons um so
the and the large countries
are actually doing cyber warfare on each
other and they know they're doing it
they're doing narrative warfare and
economic warfare so
um what i would say is that rather than
say we're in peace time i would say that
we're
in kind of a multi-polar war but that is
being fought as an unconventional rather
than conventional war so it's not being
fought kinetically
though we see mounting kinetic capacity
we see the ramping up in the
south china sea on the india china
border on you know lots of places
ai military drone technology as an arms
race everywhere
um space war type phenomena so
we're ramping the kinetic capacity but
mostly it's being fought through
economic
diplomatic info narrative cyber
type war
and so in this situation where there is
a movement from kind of
peacetime agreements to something more
like unconventional warfare
um and from in general conventional to
unconventional warfare is a more kind of
primary tactic
that has been happening over the last
couple decades globally then narrative
and info warfare become
some of the uh most central parts of
that overall picture
and especially in the info ecology where
you can
micro target affecting people right the
idea of stochastic terrorism
which is let's say i want to drive
terrorism in an area because i want to
turn the enemy on itself i want to
damage the infidel or damage the social
fabric of a place or whatever it is
but i want plausible deniability to
never have it traced to me well i can go
into a group that's radicalized with a
sock puppet right with a fake
kind of account as a international actor
or a domestic actor or whatever
and just increase the radicalization
through
kind of support that looks pretty
natural right in
be like let's say it's an incel group or
it's a
you know boogaloo group an antifa group
just be sharing more stuff that is of
the type that outrages them
celebrate the people who go do the acts
of violence more of what great heroes
they are
and what will happen is the already kind
of
on the edge unhinged people in those
groups that
are close to tipping now we tip them
over so we call it stochastic terrorism
because i don't know who will do what
harm when where but i know that i'm
increasing the pressure and the
statistical likelihood that those harms
occur
with very difficult time being able to
trace that
right so
the social media kind of
uh and and algorithmic bias kind of
thing the
uh radical asymmetric information
warfare the lack of kind of information
broadcast controls uh combined with
the increase in narrative and info
warfare combined with the actual
complexity of the problems
all of that is unique to the current
situation
that the nope you know machiavelli
didn't have to deal with these things as
much as he
had to deal with sun tzu didn't have to
deal with these things and so
uh when we think about how do we solve
any problems
the first thing we should be thinking is
how do we understand the problems well
enough to come up with good solutions
how do we make those good make sure
those good solutions don't cause other
problems
so that we don't cause problems and so
that other people who notice they cause
problems don't resist the thing we're
trying to do so how do we come up with
good solutions to the problem and the
larger context of things that matter
and how do we make sure that enough of
the world is
in conversation of the right type and
understanding in the right way
that there's support for that that
should be the background of whether i
care about social justice or the
environment or wealth inequality i
should care about this as the basis
for the possibility of effectiveness
towards it and
so then we have to say given these
things that are messing up
sense-making what would it take to start
to correct them
so what is the right relationship to the
topic of free speech
in general and specifically in
considering
how deep the information ecology issues
are to our capacity to address anything
so
i'm not going to be able to give
something like an adequate
answer but i will add complexity to the
problem
in the way we think about it here a
little bit so
it's very easy to say free speech
free speech no censorship because
whoever has the censoring capacity then
ends up just controlling
everything we don't trust anyone that
much so free speech and let people
figure it out
and we can see why historically and
there's a kind of
in in the left right dialectic that is
healthy which we don't have and the
thing that's called left and right today
don't actually mean anything right in
the
in the u.s in the counterculture
movement in the 60s
the left was more for kind of radical
speech
and free speech and the right had more
desire to control certain things that
they thought were communist or whatever
now it's almost the exact opposite the
left has things that it wants to control
they consider hate speech the right is
more for free speech
so what we even mean by left and right
are pretty broken but let's try and take
it to some foundational concepts
of there are things like
rights and responsibilities or
traditionalism and progressivism
that are both important valuable and
should be in dialectic meaning should be
in some tension and in conversation with
the right answer involves the
consideration of their relationship
not one of the sides but as soon as you
move from dialectic between them to
warfare between them
you stop seeking synthesis and you start
seeking
more um double down versions of a
partial view
right so in the kind of traditional
progressive
thing this is actually an important
thing to understand we should be
traditionalists
traditionalists means that there's kind
of an intuition
that the systems that worked for a very
long time
probably did for some good reasons they
probably
even though the people who are
traditionalists are not thinking of it
in evolutionary terms all the time
there's a sense of like
if there hadn't been some effectiveness
and wisdom in it it would have failed
and in a world where most of the other
systems did fail so why did some make it
through
and we might be mistakenly thinking we
understand the systems better than we do
and why they worked and we
seek to change them when we're actually
changing something that really worked
for a long time for a reason
so let's kind of go back to the things
that worked or let's at least make sure
we protect the things that worked for a
long time
that's kind of the traditional intuition
simplified version of it the progressive
intuition is
we're facing new problems that we've
never faced before and the old solutions
either were
inadequate as they were there were some
people that did well and some that did
really bad under it
and or even if they were adequate
they're not adequate to the changing
landscape so we need
progress and evolution and adaptation
well of course those are both right
right like of course we want to uh pay
attention to the things that worked
and make sure we understand them very
well before changing them and most the
time we understand them less well than
than we think and
in a new environment where there's new
issues we might need to assess these
things quite
differently and be able to add and be
able to amend the situation
so we want a healthy dialectic right
between uh
traditionalism and progressivism
so with regard to free speech here
there's a kind of traditional
orientation that says hey founding
fathers constitution
total free speech well in that
environment
there wasn't facebook right there wasn't
uh twitter youtube any of those types of
things
uh if if i'm in the 17th century
the 18th century and i um
use my free speech to its maximum in
that environment where i'm shouting
in a town square maybe a few hundred
people hear what i have to say
and then they can actually talk with me
we can engage and we have more shared
experience of base reality because we
live in a similar area and have seen
stuff right
now if i share something where most of
the people seeing it
don't have the same shared experience
they don't live in the same area maybe i
say that i have privileged info i saw
this or whatever it was
and this can get amplified to be seen by
millions or billions of people
that's such a different situation so the
way that
some people tristan talks about this is
that freedom of speech
should not automatically equal freedom
of reach but it's not just freedom of
reach it's
an algorithmic orientation to take the
things that hijack people the most and
up regulate those things
and so we don't see long complex thought
pieces trending anywhere near as much as
we see
emotionally charged short salacious
vehement things trending
and to understand any of these things
well they're complex enough that they
need to be long and complex and kind of
boring we
like but cognitively we are not eating
salads and healthy things cognitively
we're just eating french fries
right oriented to the maximum kind of
dopaminergic hit
so is the answer that everyone should
just share everything
in an environment that doesn't just
allow them to broadcast but will amplify
well so now we can say should the issue
be freedom of speech or the regular
regulation of those platforms now we
start to get to the right level of
granularity where we're realizing you
can't think of freedom of speech
independent of the media environment in
which the things are being upregulated
so then we say well should we actually
regulate freedom of speech
we've always thought that it was okay to
have something like an
ftc or an sec that says you're not
allowed to lie about your finances
in this public filing or in this
marketing so we were okay with
regulation online
but then as we trust the government less
the question is who is adjudicating what
is a lie
and so in a situation right now where
nobody really trusts at least half of
the government
or the other kinds of institutions
nobody would trust
who's going to say what fake news is
because the left says the rights news is
fake and the right says the left's news
is fake and everyone
says that the institutions that the
other guy follows are are the corrupted
ones
so then the question of well who gets to
adjudicate what is true
well that becomes the most powerful
force in the world and then all the most
powerful forces have maximum incentive
to become that and to capture it using
all of the
um covert influence and whatever tools
that they could possibly have to do that
so the the ins the easy sensor answers
and the easy just keep total free speech
within this context answers are both
silly
right the issue is actually pretty
complex in order to be able to
adjudicate we need
to trust the adjudication process well
that's again like a state regulating a
market here it's a market of ideas
and it's a state that would maybe like
whether it's an sec or an ftc that would
be able to regulate but you need a
people who can regulate to make sure
this is actually true and honest and
doing an effective thing so again the
basis of the answer is actually again
they call
a collective enlightenment that has
people who can sense make well enough
to be able to say how would we go about
approaching these things
[Music]
i think one of the reasons that i care
about this issue so much and
am sensitized to it is
i have experienced
being very very passionately certain
about stuff that i later realized i was
wrong about
and doing that enough times made me
reflect on the meta thing of like
why was i so certain of that thing like
so certain that i would go to infowar
over it right battle with people on it
and then is the thing that i learned
later that changed my mind did it not
exist yet
it didn't exist in my awareness right
like and
so my own fallibility in this way really
kind of made me dubious of my own
confidence and i started
uh in my epistemic process and as i
started to pay more attention to it
i was like all right i'm aware of places
where i was wrong in the past
and i'm aware of where i think almost
everybody else is wrong
but i actually can't say a single belief
that i currently hold that i think i'm
probably wrong about
lots of other people can say what they
think i'm wrong about and
in the future i'm almost certain to
think some of the stuff i think now
is wrong unless i don't learn much
but if i'm on an evolutionary path where
i'm actually learning a lot a
developmental path
i will almost certainly think some of my
best thinking right now
is naive or silly or underinformed or
something
how do we deal with that how do we deal
with the fact that no one can name a
belief they currently hold that they
think is wrong
but they can name other peoples even
though they are statistically likely to
be wrong about almost everything
at least partially wrong that's a tricky
thing right and
um there it's very easy to have an
emotional desire for certainty or for
for security
that i get through a sense of certainty
that orients me towards false premature
certainty especially given that
we didn't evolve to process this type of
in this much complexity and hyper
objects and these types of things
and yet these issues are catastrophic
today
how to fix collective sense making is a
big hard topic
and i absolutely can't say that
myself or the groups that i work with or
anyone i know has the whole thing
figured out
it's why i want more people to
understand both
how significant the problem is how much
it affects all the other problems that
you care about
and how it's upstream to those and some
of the factors contributing to it so
that more collective intelligence starts
working on various aspects of the
solution
uh there are there's a project that
we're working on right now
um that is hopefully getting within a
few months of being able to have a
minimum viable product offered and i'll
share a little bit about it here
um largely because we're actually
seeking help
and if people who are here are uh have
some capacity and
are inspired um
and otherwise we might talk about it
more once it's live and people can kind
of
interact with it
and so for
for the listeners what can you do for
better sense making
well one thing is
if there are whole chunks of populations
that you
only have pejorative strawman versions
of where you can't explain
why they think what they think without
making them dumb or bad you should be
dubious of your own modeling
uh saint francis seek first to
understand
you should seek harder to take in the
news that they're taking in for a week
right for a day go to mother jones for a
day if you're on the right go to
breitbart for a day take it in and try
to
seek if i'm continuously getting this
and i what are the issues that i face as
a being if i'm
really put myself in that person's shoes
and it's not just so you can empathize
with the dumb people it's that there's
some actual signal
that you might have been missing it
doesn't mean that it's all signal
there's also noise
most all of the positions right now have
some signal and a bunch of noise
so we want to be able to seek to
understand so we can actually get the
other humans that we need to be able to
coordinate with
and that we can get the parts of signal
we can be able to see where there's
signal and noise and we can start to
synthesize the signal across the space
right that is a movement towards
adequate sense-making or synthesis
so yeah if you feel
a combination of outraged and outraged
scared you know emotional
and very certain with a strong kind of
enemy hypothesis orientation you have
been captured by somebody's narrative
warfare
and you think it's your own thinking and
that will even if you win at a local
battle whatever technologies you use to
win
whatever social tech or info tech or
whatever you use to win the other side
will reverse engineer and come back and
you're just escalating an arms race
you're not moving towards real shared
sense making and coordination
that's one thing i would say this
doesn't mean you never take a position
it means that you take a position
that is trying not to just continue
warfare but trying to elevate the whole
space which requires me understanding
the whole space better
i would say that one of the ways to do
that is you know i don't have social
media apps on my phone i think that's
just a dumb idea i don't think any
anyone should say yeah i can take the
most addictive
drugs regularly and not get addicted um
so i don't have them there i do have
them on my computer
i'm cognizant around limiting my time
and engagement but i've also
curated it where i know what it is i
know that it's not
a just a benign tool i know it is a
ai empowered agent seeking to affect my
behavior
and so how do i uh relate to that better
so
i intentionally went and followed
i took all the major positions extreme
left moderate left ex
moderate right extreme right conspiracy
the chinese views the
russian views et cetera and i followed
all of them
right followed all those news sources
followed the thought leaders in them
and made sure that i had a pretty good
distribution so facebook's algorithm is
very confused by me right
and the other kinds of algorithms
because i wanted to see that i was
not getting an echo chamber when i
use facebook i mostly don't state things
i put out questions
one of the reasons that i put out
questions is because the people that
i also friended people who have almost
every view and so many people in this
environment have said if you believe
such and such unfriend me or i'm
unfriending you
so they're doubling down on their tiny
little tribalist group think right
because the other people are such
dumb terrible bad people i don't even
want to be friends with you and see your
nonsense
this is not how you influence the world
effectively
and so i've intentionally friended
people across the space and followed
them
so they also see my stuff so the comment
thread will not be a filter bubble it'll
be some extreme right and some extreme
left and some various kinds of views
someone could say well how dare you
amplify such and such because
if you don't understand what swaths of
humanity is thinking
your ability to influence humanity is
very poor your ability to even
understand it is very poor
so then i ask the question so as to
hopefully break filter bubbles
if someone reads the comment thread and
is exposed to things that they aren't
exposed to on their own news feed
to at least maybe inspire some people to
look at something else no unfortunately
almost everyone who comments even if
they hold different views share such
poor quality comments because they're
just they're triggered and oriented
to do some kind of limbic hijacked thing
that they don't even make a constructive
enough argument that it's all that
compelling
this one of the things you'll notice is
that
we're not compelled by stuff because we
did formal epistemology and
propositional logic on it
we're compelled because it feels truthy
to us
um or feels consequential and so
like if you'll notice that the stuff
that feels so obviously true to you
feels obviously true to people who
already believe what you believe and
feels obviously not true to the other
people when you put it out they
instantly see it as propaganda
gibberish right and so that's not
communicating
that's just doubling down on groupthink
and tribalism
and so but it's interesting to see why
is it that
and good to certain people and feels
just like
stupid and evil to other people why does
it feel
that different way well if i pay
attention to the media environment that
they're taking in
feels true is largely resonant with what
they've taken in so far
right like that's a big part of it so um
one of the things that i do on an issue
is
let's say i want to make sense of
police violence in the u.s or i want to
make sense of
the beirut blast or the india china
border or whatever it is
as far as narratives go there's not one
narrative there's usually
there's usually not even two narratives
there might be five
or seven or eleven different kind of
narrative clusters there might be a
hundred
versions but they fall within general
clusters
and so what i'll usually try to do is do
a landscape of what the narrative
clusters are first
and then i'll try to steal man each
narrative
like what is the strongest version of
arguing that thing
that i've been able to see so look for
the best thinkers that are
representative of those narratives
that's helpful for me to both see the
signal that they got because that
the collective intelligence of those
people doesn't have no signal
it also helps me understand why they
think what they think which also helps
me understand how to maybe communicate
and relate but that doesn't mean that i
agree with all of it it means that i'm
seeking to understand it right
so then the next thing i want to do is
after i've done that which is a kind of
interpersonal intelligence
seeking to understand the narrative then
i want to do a kind of empirical or
objective intelligence
and break the narrative into individual
propositions
and typically even framed in the
question are assumptions and
presuppositions that are actually
propositions so use propositional logic
and break it into individual
propositions and i say
what evidence have they put forward to
support each of these propositions and
typically it's like
i'll break a complex narrative into like
50 propositions and there's maybe
evidence for like four of them
and it's usually like maybe strong
evidence for two and kind of weak for
four and then a bunch of just
emotional leaps logical leaps so then
i'll say what
additional evidence can i get that will
either
verify or falsify or at least support or
decrease the likelihood for any of these
and where are there ones that i can
neither verify nor falsify and should
just sit as
this is just a filler someone put in but
i have no basis for certainty whatsoever
i have to be comfortable with
uncertainty to be able to make sense of
it or i will try to jump to false
certainties
then i have to not only seek to verify
and falsify each of those parts
because most likely there's a few true
parts a few nonsense parts and a bunch
of filler
right and that's true across the whole
narrative space so then i also have to
seek to do this across the other
narratives
so this is important because
most people are jumping to what is true
very much not through a epistemic or
logical process even if they think
it is what they if they really break it
down propositionally they'll find that
they had a
logical process of this seems true and
this seems true therefore and therefore
has like eight
logical leaps in it um
so basically these are a few steps that
i would encourage
for people on their own to be dubious of
their
own certainty and
outrage to seek to understand the
narrative landscape better to seek
empiricism better to
try to be able to not reject or
take entire narratives but be able to
look for partial truths
to be able to try to aggregate signal
across the space
to be way more comfortable with
uncertainty and that's uncomfortable in
a way to say
i don't understand the world i live in
even in the most consequential areas i
just don't understand it
at least that i actually feel safer
because i know that i don't have
confirmation bias making me understand
it wrongly
i at least have a chance to increase my
understanding
when i say i don't know because the
moment i think that i falsely know
now i'm not even going to be able to
learn well right
so these are some examples of things and
then
in addition to reading across the space
actually seek the more
um well-grounded and complex views as
opposed to the more trending ones
uh i want to find the thinkers that seem
most earnest
and most well kind of educated and
thoughtful across the space and then i
want to see where people who have deep
expertise and earnestness
disagree and then i want to explore the
basis of the disagreement
so just a few basic principles and we've
talked about this you've had other
whole videos on sense making practices
but these are a few basic things
the reason why i feel compelled to say
this is because we were getting into the
project we're going to do and the
project we're
working on by no means can do everything
and it doesn't exist
up yet so i want the first thing to be
empowering people to work on on their
own
so the thing that we're doing is trying
to do something like
a better version of the fourth estate a
better version of news that is
relevant to the actual information
landscape of the current moment
and the critical aspects of education
that people didn't get that are
most helpful for them to be able to
understand uh
and sense make the world better on their
own and
we didn't actually start off thinking
that we'd be doing something like
news or media we started out thinking
that we were doing something like
the kind of intelligence and research
work to be able to understand the
escalation pathways to catastrophic risk
so we were working on getting a much
better sense of
supply chain fragilities and food
security issues and
uh the escalation pathways to different
kinds of war and
and that that's not just at a
theoretical level but having to get a
lot of detailed info about what's really
going on on the ground
to know where the actual escalation
pathways and those types of things are
as we were and that was to inform
strategic
kinds of interventions that could really
help address it
to be able to address it you're going to
talk to people who are in
decision-making positions
and share information with them to
hopefully try to influence them in
different ways and so we had the
opportunity to do that and speak to
people in
in high level public and private
influence positions and prepare
information for them
and the information we're preparing the
kind of briefings of those type
take a tremendous amount of very skilled
people's
time to create actionable intel for
someone who can make choices that are
quite consequential
and we were able to see that we could
actually provide pretty novel insights
in a number of areas because
we weren't looking at the global issues
in
um specialized siloed ways where a lot
of say
you know the issues are more complex
than the institutional structures were
designed for
and so you would have cdc looking at
you know disease type risks and these
kind of military groups looking at these
kinds of
terrorism risks and these groups looking
at cyber risks and but we see a world
where something can start in one area
and start to cascade across them
and so looking at the interconnection of
them is actually critical to understand
the world well so we were looking at
taking a
um a deeply kind of interdisciplinary
and trans-narrative
perspective on this that actually
resulted in
um
novel insights into a bunch of spaces
and
one of the things that started to occur
during that was
this is actually what news should be
like high-level
intelligence briefings some things
should be national security or whatever
but um the idea of a decision maker
who gets a lot of information processing
is a fundamentally anti-democratic idea
right a
democratic idea would be everyone can
possibly be a significant decision maker
hopefully
is actually more involved in the
processes of being able to influence
but the basis of being able to make good
choices
is the information processing not the
information access this is a key thing
a lot of people will share this idea
that
i can pull up my smartphone and have
access to more total information than
the president had 20 years ago and so
we've democratized information access
this is kind of a gibberish story
because even though in one way it's true
i can't read the billion search results
on anything and i don't know where the
really relevant stuff is and i can't
process you know all of the information
so it's not access to information it's
access to information processing
to inform actionable intel that is
really relevant and there's an
unbelievable asymmetry of that if you
look at the top
kind of trading funds algorithmic
trading funds and you look at the kind
of
financial market intel in information
processing not just information access
yes they have information access you
don't have of lots of different kinds of
things behind pay walls and privileged
information
but then they also have massive ais that
are
processing doing machine learning on
tremendous databases of stuff to be able
to
um high-speed trade bundles of complex
financial instruments that front run
you know other groups compared to the
average person's ability
to understand the market we might be
talking about like 10 orders of
magnitude information processing
difference
and the same is true when it comes to
you know
all different aspects of power and
intelligence
so to really be able to support a
an emergence of something like a
democratic process participatory
governance the information
access and information processing to be
able to understand the issues well
enough
to know what good informed action looks
like is prerequisite
and so we started thinking well can we
can we make
things like this as the news and
at the same time one of the risks that
we were seeing that was driving all of
the other catastrophic risks the fastest
was the news landscape
and i don't just mean the few large news
channels i mean
the media landscape that is the facebook
issues we were talking about
and you know all the youtube
recommendation
algorithms plus the nature of the news
and all like that and we're seeing that
you know people being willing to go up
in arms over
uh mass squaring or shutdown or
hydroxychloroquine or
systemic race issues mostly are from
things they saw on their screen
not things that they experienced
directly in their town so
the nature of what was happening in the
media space
was actually driving the breakdown of
society faster than anything else was
because in the movement from
conventional unconventional warfare the
bottom of the stack is economic warfare
that's where the real resource power
comes
the back of the stack that backs it up
at the end of the day if it has to is
kinetic warfare guns and stuff
but the front of it where the fastest
rate of change is occurring
is the narrative in info warfare that is
being fought in people's minds for
people's minds right for
the the control of population
and so if we could do something to
just even slow down the rate of
polarization and radicalization just
take some of the pollution out of the
narrative and info space if we could
show the narrative in info weapons
because they
only work as well when they're covert
when they're made over when you get to
see
how the different types of spin work and
how the different kinds of data
manipulation work
people can start recognizing them more
in recognizing how they're being
affected by them
and be affected less at least have the
possibility of engagement with it
and then if you can start having even a
small group of people who are really
endeavoring to
and getting the skills to and the
information processing support
to understand the world much better plus
have much higher quality conversation
with each other
that group starts to have a collective
intelligence that really is asymmetric
to
most of the rest of the population that
can start coming up with better
solutions and become a strange attractor
which is the beginning of drive a
cultural enlightenment that can
re-instantiate the possibility of
participatory
coordination govern governance and so
the current thing that we're building
that will almost certainly not be
what it ends up being as we see what do
people really respond to and what gets
traction
has a few different kinds of information
products together
one is something that is like news
meaning
addressing critical current events and
you know if you look at big news
organizations they're huge organizations
right like it's a lot of resource to try
to do that you know you've worked at bbc
and big organizations
uh
and so if you for most people they would
actually
be best supported by having very good
local news because they could if they
could actually make better sense of
their local world they would
have more agency to do stuff about it
but local news across everywhere
is just an unbelievably tremendous job
right
tremendously large job and being able to
have
news that is kind of eurocentric and
asian-centric and whatever and across
all the sectors is a lot so
though rather than pick like one domain
that we're starting in we're starting
with
uh the most consequential things across
areas from a global perspective
with a somewhat u.s centric audience we
have to pick somewhere to start
so what that means is domestic politics
and geopolitics and economies and
markets culture technology environment
uh military all of those things where
we're looking at what are the things
that we believe are tier one
consequential
in terms of how much they can change the
overall
nature of life in the world you know in
the coming years and decades
and being able to present that in the
form of
what looked like briefings across you
know this week
in the the happenings that happened that
are of top consequence
that doesn't have and you know where we
don't have
on the ground report networks that are
anywhere near as robust as we want we're
working on building those out but
largely we're looking at
groups that are reporting on it and
being able to
look across the whole space and be able
to say factoring
left and right and different countries
perspectives and do that kind of
synthesis
what is the clearest thing that we can
say with confidence
and so we're looking at things that are
maximally consequential and what we can
say
with confidence that actually is
calibrated from a kind of formal process
that
is trans ideology trans narrative rather
than supporting a particular political
agenda or economic agenda
and it's designed to be a second
simplicity meaning a lot of complexity
of research goes into it but it's
actually
as simple to understand as possible so
there's a low barrier of entry of
starting to get something that doesn't
have narrative spin or
info manipulation in it now if someone
wants to go deeper and someone could
easily ask well why would i trust that
as opposed to anything else
we would say you're not trusting us
because we're a particular authority
we're hoping that you trust your own
sense making progressively better and
we're showing you in detail
transparently how we do our sense making
so
how we currently have it structured is
that someone can see that briefing
and then one of the there's different
places they can go to go deeper one of
them is a under the hood feature
where they can see the epistemic process
the sense making process we used to come
up with that so what things did we read
and look at
what data sets did we include what data
sets did we say we had low confidence in
and decided to throw out or
put a discount rate on and what
epistemic frames did we use
and so if someone wants to see that they
can so now this is them also learning
how are we making sense of the world so
they can both give us feedback on hey i
think you miss weighted this data set or
there's this other data center frame
awesome but they can also be learning i
guess i could have done that i could
have looked at all of those sources i
could have applied these frames i didn't
even know some of those frames now that
i know them
so they're increasing in their own sense
making capacity by seeing
how we're doing it of course we also
uh want to show retrospectives of where
we made forecasts or said
what was going on where we later found
out that we were wrong or right or we
get to show here's where we were wrong
here's where we were right
where we were wrong how are we updating
our models so really good transparency
and earnestness in that whole process
also so you can do the kind of under the
hood thing you can also do the meta news
thing
the meta news is okay so here's what we
were able to find out about this topic
but that sounds different than what you
read in the new york times or the
atlantic or breitbart or mother jones or
rt or whatever other place you're
looking at
why what do they say why do they say
that why did we come up with something
different what is our assessment of what
they came up with
so this is actually and of course we're
not going to be able to do that for all
news sources right we we've already
looked at about 1500 new sources in our
curation process we kind of have to
collapse those to ones that cluster
in a similar type of narrative and then
pick you know some of the better
exemplars of those
and say okay so here's the narrative
landscape
we'll go ahead and steel man that
narrative landscape and then we will
break it down
into individual propositions and say
what can we verify what can we falsify
so we are helping people to understand
the world through more of the lenses
understand why people other people think
what they think even have a clear sense
of it
then also understand how to empirically
validate
these things then we also show the
narrative and info weapons so we'll say
okay so in this piece here
here's the original piece of science
that they were quoting or the original
video
or that they were referencing but then
here's the way they framed it this is
lakehoff framing this is a kind of spin
now that same thing is has spin on it
over here that's of a different type so
let's explain the concept of lakehoff
framing and spin
and or russell conjugation or those
kinds of narrative weapons and say
look for these everywhere right and this
isn't the left saying the right
snooze is fake or the right saying the
left news is fake this is saying
everyone who's playing the narrative
game is subject to some of the same
pressures
and these are some of the tools that get
used so look for them
and also there's some signal in all of
these places
so we're not coming out as the this is
fake news but
there is some signal let's try to verify
it and there is some distortion
so the goal in the meta news is that
someone doesn't hear what we say and say
okay well that's just one other
narrative with lots of narratives they
actually get to see all the narratives
and they get to see how we're making
sense of them
and they get to also apply their own
capacity to make sense of them
and we make explicit the narrative and
info weapons
so that people can recognize them more
on their own
and by also by reifying the true parts
and being able to say where something is
either clearly falsifiable or we just
can neither verify nor falsify it's just
conjecture or spin we hopefully help
people neither just
accept nor reject any standard narrative
but be able to take a more rigorous and
nuanced view across all of them
[Music]
then of course there's places where to
understand what's going on
there's education that people need for
frames right like they need some history
around this india china border conflict
or they need to understand certain
things around
why the high altitude place where the
watershed is and missile defense and
whatever would be the strategic targets
they are
or um so we'll also do either
curate if there's a perfect educational
piece
that really does a very good job or a
few we'll curate those but we'll also
create
pieces that provide the critical aspects
of education that peop most people
didn't get
and where we also try to do kind of a
pareto optimization on this so it's like
say we're talking here about the
facebook issues and there's stuff
trending in the news around what's
happening with fake news and facebook
whatever
so if someone's read marshall mcluhan
they're going to understand things about
media theory that other people aren't
going to have but not everybody's going
to go read mcluhan
and we want to be able to reference
mcluhan for media theory but also lake
off for media theory
and then gerard for conflict theory and
other types of conflict theory and
poetry for institutional decay but also
strauss howe and tainter for
institutional decay there's a lot of
things
where those epistemic frames give you
the ability to understand stuff better
but people aren't going to go read all
those books so
can we take the critical model that
gives a lot of help in that book and
make a
three or ten page essay that kind of
gives the
most epistemic reifying power
in the easiest information compression
and say if you want to read the whole
book
please do otherwise here's at least some
basic stuff similar with the history
pieces and the context pieces
so this is hoping to be able to give it
easy low barrier of entry overview of
critical things
with progressively deeper capacities to
learn sense making and epistemology and
the kinds of background necessary to
understand the world better
now this is in a way this is like a big
project and ambitious and another way
it's just trying to do broadcast news
and education right
right um which is almost going back to
something
uh so the decentralized aspect because
it's centralized right
the wikipedia thing is hard to control
but you can control for a smaller team
of people that have really quality
epistemics and
knowledge process and we've been able to
bring together a really exceptional team
and are continuing to
look for and grow that it's actually
hard to find people who can do this
because like to do the core sense making
work
we need people who are
capable of doing two things well one
is trans narrative right that they are
not so emotionally captured by a
particular narrative that they can
actually do a really good job of
steel manning all of the narratives and
so that's kind of a intersubjective
intelligence
and then on the objective side we need
people who can do empiricism well
across in an interdisciplinary way
across
multiple disciplines because if i want
to understand almost any of these issues
the lens of finance is critical but not
sufficient
the lens of culture is critical but not
sufficient the lens
of um narrative warfare or politics or
whatever so there's
quite a lot of environmental psychology
or infrastructure there's
a lot of different specialty domains
that need to be
factored so there's a lot of narratives
and a lot of epistemologies
so we're looking for people internally
who can do
uh interdisciplinary and trans-narrative
thinking so then of course people who
are specialists or do hold a particular
ideology can give
input but we can take the input across
those spaces and try to do
analysis and then synthesis on it
the decentralized sense making is
something that we want to
experiment with we're actually um
yeah looking at being able to uh
crowdsource different projects and be
able to help up regulate some of the
right ones and
you know even where you have articles
that have forums
can we experiment with architectures in
the forum that incent
both higher quality sentence making and
higher quality conversation where those
are the things that get up regulated
um i think we can and we have a number
of kind of ideas on how to make
architectures that really incent that
social architectures built in the
digital space
and so the hope here is that let's say
that it's a small percentage of the
total audience
that spends a lot of time and that
really has the high epistemic drive and
capacity to sense make very well
well even if it's a small percentage of
the total audience
some of those people are in everybody's
friend group almost everybody's friend
group almost every major facebook group
or social network
if those people have really good data
sources much better epistemology things
that are addressing well
all of the sides of various things and
they're learning how to do dialectic and
steel manning well they can start to
influence the spaces they're in to be
able to do better sense making
often times the people who have best
sense making are also employed by the
people who are in top institutional
positions of power as strategists and
analysts or whatever
to be able to influence those things so
basically the information commons is not
being stewarded
we're trying to do something to start
stewarding the information commons
and to make that a strange attractor of
more things that will start to do that
that's why this is a non-profit project
is we're not willing to ever put ads on
we're not willing to put it behind a
paywall that makes it not accessible to
everyone to really democratize the
access to the
that quality of information processing
has to be freely available to everyone
we also aren't willing to take any prof
non-profit funds that have any strings
attached
so it has to be people that actually
believe that increasing
decentralized collective intelligence is
not good for the world and authentically
want to support that as a commons
project
and that's you know what we're seeking
right now is people who
either like if there are people who
would want to put capital into that
that's a timely need
if there are people who have really
exceptional
analytic capabilities or access to
really novel kind of
source of information or data sets or
have worked on machine deep learning
types of technologies for sense making
those are the kinds of
connections and alliances that would be
say
reach out if you're aligned land our
ability to make sense of the world
is breaking down we're making more and
more consequential choices
with worse and worse sense making to
inform those choices
which is kind of running increasingly
fast
through the woods increasingly blind
over the last two years rebel wisdom has
interviewed some of the world's top
thinkers
now we've brought them together for an
eight-week online course
sensemaking 101 with daniel
schmacktenberger
diane mushaw hamilton john viveki
doshin roshi and more improve your
sense-making
develop your sovereignty and join a
wider community
looking to do the same
[Music]